Guide to the Hiram P. Merville papers 1861-1897 (bulk 1862-1865)
Brown University Library
Hiram P. Merville papers
Merville (Hiram P.) papers
1861-1897
(bulk 1862-1865)
Ms.96.4
John Hay Library University Archives and Manuscripts Box A Brown University Providence, RI, 02912 Telephone: Manuscripts: 401-863-3723; University Archives: 401-863-2148 Email: Manuscripts: hay@brown.edu; University Archives: archives@brown.edu
0.25 linear feet
Merville, Hiram P.
The Merville papers consist of 19 letters of Hiram P. Merville to family and friends, and one letter from a friend to Hiram, during the years 1861 or 1862 to 1865. The collection also includes a booklet from the 1897 reunion of the First New York Dragoons, the unit in which Hiram served during the Civil War.
Biographical/Historical Note
Hiram P. Merville was born in China, New York in 1840. At the time of his father's death in 1860, he was one of Jacob Merville's four surviving children. He enlisted in the First Regiment of New York Dragoons (previously the 130th Regiment New York Volunteer Infantry) in 1862, at which time he gave his occupation as farming. He was discharged a corporal in August 1865.
He became a physician after the war, and in 1867 married Emma Jane Wilkison in Eagle Valley, New York. They had two daughters, Beulah (Mrs. Charles W. Spofford) and Susan (Mrs. Herbert J. Droppers). They soon went west, settling in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, where Hiram practiced medecine until his death in 1908. He is buried in the Forest Home Cemetery in that city.
Many of these letters were written to Hiram's brother Charles, and often mention another brother named Fayette. It is probable that the Harry referred to in the letters refers to his brother Harrison.
Hiram had no sister named Em. It is likely that this recipient of his letters was his future wife Emma Jane, five years his junior, and a schoolteacher before their marriage. Emma Jane was born in Aztalan, Wisconsin, where her father died after the family had moved there from New York. Emma Jane's mother returned to New York after her husband's death and married her husband's uncle, Nathan Round.
Collection information
The Merville papers consist of 19 letters of Hiram P. Merville to family and friends, and one letter from a friend to Hiram, during the years 1861 or 1862 to 1865. The collection also includes a booklet from the 1897 reunion of the First New York Dragoons, the unit in which Hiram served during the Civil War.
The collection was given to Brown University Library by Jane Spofford Chafee in 1982. ?????
There are no restrictions on access, except that the collection can only be seen by prior appointment. Some materials may be stored off-site and cannot be produced on the same day on which they are requested.
Series 1. Correspondence; Series 2. Printed items; Items within Series 1 are ordered chronologically.
Administrative information
The collection was given to Brown University Library by Jane Spofford Chafee in 1982.
Additional information
John Hay Library, University Archives and Manuscripts
Names
Chafee, Jane Spofford
Subjects
Merville family; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 130th; United States. Army. New York Cavalry Regiment, 19th; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Soldiers--Correspondence
Occupations
Soldiers
- Merville, Hiram P. to [unknown][unknown] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  2 pages on 1 leaf; fragment: final pages of letter; letter ends, "Do the best for me you can. More anon. Hiram"
- Merville, Hiram P. to Merville, Charles ("Dear Bro. C.")[no place], [no date] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  4 pages on 1 leaf; leaf discolored by stains; stationery bears embossed image of a horse; letter begins, "No. 1 came to me some days ago."
- Merville, Hiram P. to Merville, Charles ("Dear Brother Charles")Camp of the 130th New York Volunteers, [no date] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  2 pages on 1 leaf; ink is very faded; leaf has creases, minor tears, and some stains
- Merville, Hiram P. to Wilkison, Emma Jane? ("Em my sister")Headquarters of the 130th Regiment of the New York State Volunteers, [no year] March 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  2 pages on 1 leaf
- Merville, Hiram P. to Merville, Charles? ("My brother")Headquarters of the 130th Regiment of the New York State Volunteers, [no year] March 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  3 pages on 1 leaf
- Merville, Hiram P. to Merville, Charles ("Dear Bro. Chas.")Camp of the 19th New York Cavalry, [no year] September 24 ("Eve of Sept. 24th"), 28 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Merville, Hiram P. to Merville, Charles and Wilkison, Emma Jane? ("Dear Bro. Chas. & Sister Em")Camp Thorpe, Suffolk, Virginia, [no year] September 27; Sunday morn[ing; 1862 September 28?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  4 pages on 1 leaf
- Merville, Hiram P. to Merville, Charles ("Dear Brother Charles")Camp of the 130th New York Volunteers (See transcription; letter may read "130th Regt"), [no year] [December 24] ("Christmas Eve") (Box 1, Folder 8)
  5 pages on 1 leaf; ink is very faded; leaf discolored by stains; stationery bears embossed image (of a horse?)
- Merville, Hiram P. to Merville, Charles ("Dear Brother Charles")Camp of the 130th New York Volunteers, 1862 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  2 pages on 1 leaf; small rips and tear at bottom of leaf; stationery bears imbossed image at upper left
- Merville, Hiram P. to "Dear Friends"Camp Thorpe, Suffolk, Virginia, 1862 September 19-20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  4 pages on 1 leaf; stationery bears image at upper left of page 1
- Merville, Hiram P. to Charles Merville ("Dear Bro. Charles")Headquarters of the 130th Regiment of the New York State Volunteers, 1862 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  2 pages on 1 leaf; ink is faded
- Merville, Hiram P. to Wilkison, Emma Jane? ("My Sister")Camp Thorpe, Suffolk, Virginia [?], 1863 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Merville, Hiram P. to Charles Merville ("Dear brother Charles")Headquarters of the 130th Regiment of the New York State Volunteers; Williamsburg, Virginia, 1863 June 8, 9, 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Merville, Hiram P. to Wilkison, Emma Jane? ("Dear Sister")Headquarters of the 19th New York Volunteer Cavalry, 1863 September 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Merville, Hiram P. to Charles Merville ("Dear Bro. Charles")Camp of the 1st New York Dragoons ("Dragons"), near Culpeper, Virginia ("Culpepper"), 1863 December 11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Merville, Hiram P. to Charles Merville ("Dear Bro. Charles")Near Culpeper, Virginia, 1863 December 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  2 pages on 1 leaf; letter seems to be missing one or more pages; stationery bears embossed image in upper right-hand corner of page 1
- Hunt, R. J. to Charles Merville [?] ("Dear Friend")Rossville, Georgia [?], 1864 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  4 pages on 1 leaf; return address: 34th Illinois Regiment Infantry [?] ("34th Ills. Vets. [?] Vols.", 2nd Brigade, 2nd Division, Department of the Cumberland (see http://civilwararchive.com/Unreghst/unilinf3.htm#34th)
- Merville, Hiram P. to Wilkison, Emma Jane? ("Dear Sis. Em.")Near City Point, Virginia ("Wagon Train, Cavalry Corps"), 1864 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  4 pages on 1 leaf; City Point, Virginia, later annexed by city of Hopwell, Virginia, served as headquarters of Union Army during Siege of Petersburg during Richmond-Petersburg Campaign of 1864-1865
- Merville, Hiram P. to Merville, Charles ("Dear bro."), Wilkison, Emma Jane ("wife"), and others Buffalo, New York, 1865 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  4 pages on 1 leaf; written from General Hospital, Buffalo, New York; also addressed to "Flora", "Etta", and "Allie May"; includes news of reaction to Abraham Lincoln's assassination
- Typescript transcription of Merville, Hiram P.'s letter to Merville, Charles; Wilkison, Emma Jane; Flora; Etta; and Allie May Buffalo, New York, 1865 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  3 pages on 3 leaves; date is that of original letter; with annotations in red pencil
- Merville, Hiram P. to Merville, Charles ("Dear Bro. Charles")Buffalo, New York, 1865 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  4 pages on 1 leaf; written from General Hospital, Buffalo, New York; includes discussion of Abraham Lincoln
- Typescript transcription of Merville, Hiram P.'s letter to Merville, Charles Buffalo, New York, 1865 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  2 pieces, stapled together; date is that of original letter; with annotations in blue ink
- Envelope addressed to Merville, Charles K.Buffalo, New York, 1865 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  1 piece; postmarked Buffalo, New York, 1865 June 29; written from East Java, Wyoming County, New York; stamp cut out
- 28th Annual Reunion, First New York Dragoons (previously 130th Regiment New York Volunteer Infantry)Buffalo, New York?, 1897 August 23-28 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Reunion booklet, with roster of First New York Dragoons; HPM is listed on page 18 with his name given incorrectly as "Merville, H. B."
- Transcriptions of letters of Hiram P. Merville and other family members (bound in booklet) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  1 item